<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The re-publicans and others spurious good old cause, briefly and truly anatomized. To preserve our native country, kingdom, legal government, Church, parliaments, laws, liberties, privileges of Parliament, and Protestant religion from ruine, scandal, and perpetual infamy; to reform, reclaim all Jesuit-ridden seduced republicans, officers, soldiers, sectaries, heretofore, or now engaged in the prosecution of this misintituled good old cause, from any future pursute thereof, and engage them for ever to abominate it, as apparently tending to publike ruin, their own temporal and eternal condemnation, infamy, our religions reproach, in present and succeeding ages. By William Prynne Esq; a bencher of Lincolns Inne.</title>
            <author>Prynne, William, 1600-1669.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 65 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56197</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P4052</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R234922</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863281</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863281</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115471</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56197)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115471)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 146:E983[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The re-publicans and others spurious good old cause, briefly and truly anatomized. To preserve our native country, kingdom, legal government, Church, parliaments, laws, liberties, privileges of Parliament, and Protestant religion from ruine, scandal, and perpetual infamy; to reform, reclaim all Jesuit-ridden seduced republicans, officers, soldiers, sectaries, heretofore, or now engaged in the prosecution of this misintituled good old cause, from any future pursute thereof, and engage them for ever to abominate it, as apparently tending to publike ruin, their own temporal and eternal condemnation, infamy, our religions reproach, in present and succeeding ages. By William Prynne Esq; a bencher of Lincolns Inne.</title>
                  <author>Prynne, William, 1600-1669.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year of our Lord, 1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>In this edition the title page has an ornamental border. Quire A comes in two settings, one of which has two states; quire B has two states or printings; and quire C has two settings, one with two states. Quire A: (1) title as above (Wing P4052), or (2) title begins "The re-publicans and others supekious [sic] good old cause. .." (Wing P2052A). Setting 1 either (a) has or (b) lacks marginal note on A3v. Quire B: B1v first note is lettered (1) "q" or (2) "I". Quire C: C1r lines 2-3 have (1a) "have denounced" or (1b, different state) "have d denounced" or (2, different setting) "have c denounced".</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May. 13".</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the British Library and the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prynne, William, 1600-1669 --  Bibliography --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115471:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE RE-PUBLICANS AND OTHERS SPURIOUS Good Old Cauſe, briefly and truly Anatomized.</p>
            <p>To preſerve our <hi>Native Country, Kingdom, legal Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Church,</hi> Parliaments, Laws, Liberties, Privileges of Parliament, and Proteſtant Religion from ruine, ſcandal, and perpetual infamy; to reform, reclaim all <hi>Jeſuit-ridden</hi> ſeduced <hi>Republicans, Officers, Soldiers, Sectaries,</hi> heretofore, or now engaged in the <hi>proſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of this miſintituled <hi>Good Old Cauſe,</hi> from any future purſute thereof, and engage them for ever to <hi>abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate it,</hi> as apparently tending to publike ruin, their own <hi>temporal</hi> and <hi>eternal condemnation, infamy,</hi> our Religions Reproach, in preſent and ſucceeding ages.</p>
            <p>By WILLIAM PRYNNE <abbr>Eſq</abbr> a Bencher of Lincolns Inne.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Jer. 6.15. c. 8.12.</bibl>
               <p>Were they aſhamed when they had commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted abomination? nay, they were not at all aſhamed, neither could they bluſh: Therefore they ſhall fall among them that fall, at the time that I ſhall viſit them, they ſhall be caſt down, ſaith the Lord.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Prov: 29.1.</bibl>
               <p>He that being often reproved hardeneth his neck, ſhall ſuddenly be deſtroyed, and that without remedy.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Zech: 7.9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14.</bibl>
               <p>Execute true judgement, &amp;c. and let none of you imagine evil against his brother in your heart. But they refuſed to hearken, and pulled away the ſhoulder, and ſtopped their ears that they ſhould not hear. Yea, they made their hearts as an adamant stone, lest they ſhould hear the Law and words which the Lord of hosts hath ſent in his Spirit by the former Prophets: Therfore came a great wrath fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lord of hoſts, who ſcattered them with a whirlwind</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Numb. 16.26, 27.</bibl>
               <p>And Moſes ſpake unto the Congregation, ſaying, Depart I pray you, from the tents of theſe wicked men, and touch nothing of theirs, leſt ye be conſumed in all their ſins. So they gat up from the Tabernacle of Korah, Dathan and Abiram, on every ſide.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year of our Lord, 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:115471:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115471:2"/>
            <head>The <hi>Republicans</hi> and others ſpurious <hi>Good Old Cauſe</hi> briefly and truly <hi>anatomiſed.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT is not only an <hi>Evangelical counſel,</hi> but <hi>Precept,</hi> which every <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciencious Chriſtian,</hi> as well in point of <hi>conſcience</hi> as <hi>prudence,</hi> is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged ſtrictly to purſue, 1 Theſ. 5.21, 22. <hi>Prove all things: hold faſt that which is good: abſtain from all appearance of evil:</hi> this being the diſtinguiſhing character between a real Wiſe-man and a Fool: Prov. 14.15, 16. <hi>The ſimple believeth every word, but the prudent man look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth well to his goings. A wife man feareth and departeth from evill, but the fool rageth and is confident.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This conſideration put me upon a ſerious ſcrutiny of the <hi>Good Old Cauſe,</hi> newly cryed up, highly magnified, and violently purſued, not only in ſundry printed <hi>Pamphlets</hi> and Petitions, but alſo in the laſt <hi>convention</hi> at <hi>Weſtminster</hi> by the confederated <hi>Triumuirate</hi> of <hi>Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licans, Sectaries,</hi> and <hi>Souldiers,</hi> pre-engaged in its purſuit, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring (like thoſe old <hi>ſeditious Seducers,</hi> whom the Apoſtle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeched the <hi>Roman</hi> Saints both to <hi>mark and avoyd,</hi> Rom. 16.17, 18.) <hi>by good words and fair ſpeeches to deceive the hearts of the ſimple</hi> Souldiers, People, and ſome of the wiſer ſort of Members, Citizens, and Army-Officers, yet diſſenting from them, to engage them to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpouſe ſo <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Old</hi> a <hi>Cauſe,</hi> ſet out with glorious general words and painted varniſhes; without acquainting them particularly, really and ingeniouſly what it is.</p>
            <p>When I had not only ſuperficially viewed the <hi>outſide,</hi> but conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately penetrated into the true <hi>original, ſeminal ſourſe,</hi> and <hi>intrals of it,</hi> I diſcovered it to be in truth the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> &amp; <hi>old Gunpowder-Traytors,</hi> moſt execrable <hi>Plot and Cauſe,</hi> principally projected and ſecretly promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Popiſh Cardinals, Jeſuites, Prieſts, Agents of all ſorts, but vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly carried on and effected, by Apoſtate Republican, and Sectari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Members of the late long Parliament, Army, and their confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, to <hi>blow up, ſubvert, destroy the King, Queen, Prince, Royal posterity, Lords, commons, Kingdom, Government, Laws, Liberty, and Property of the People of England,</hi> yea the verie <hi>constitution, freedom, power, privileges of all true</hi> Engliſh-Parliaments, <hi>the church and ministry of England,</hi> and <hi>true Protestant Religion</hi> it ſelf, formerly eſtabliſhed, to ſet up <hi>Oligarchy, Anarchy, Tyranny, Oppreſsion, Libertiniſme, Marſhal-Government, and all kind of Hereſies, Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies, Religions, Sects,</hi> yea <hi>Atheiſme, Popery</hi> it ſelf at laſt in their ſteads, to bring our <hi>Kingdoms, Churches, Nations, Religion</hi> to inevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table deſolation, and ſubject them to the Iron yokes of <hi>Rome, France,</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:115471:3"/>and <hi>Spain,</hi> for the future, The blackeſt, horridſt infernall cauſe ever yet owned by any Chriſtians, or treacherous perfidious Sons of <hi>Adam</hi> ſince the Creation.</p>
            <p>This needs no better nor clearer demonſtration, than the review of all their late treacherous perjurious actings, proceedings, (contrary to all their former Oaths of <hi>Supremacy</hi> and <hi>Allegiance, Protestation, Vow, League, covenant, Declarations, Remonstrances,</hi> new Acts of Parliament, yea the very<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> clauſes of the <hi>Writs, Indentures</hi> by which they were chooſen and retorned Members, and the Commiſsions whereby they were firſt made Army-Officers) not only againſt the late beheaded King and his poſterity, but <hi>Monarchy</hi> it ſelf (the<note n="*" place="margin">Deut. 17.14, 15. Ezech. 16, 13, 14. Jer. 17.25. c. 21.3, 4.</note> beſt of <hi>Governments</hi>) being that of<note n="(a)" place="margin">Pſ. 10.16. Pſ. 29.10. Pſ 47.7. 1 Tim. 1.17.</note> 
               <hi>God himſelf</hi> over the whole World, and of<note n="(b)" place="margin">Pſ. 2.6. pſ. 24.9, 10 pſ. 45 14, 15. pſ. 149. 2. Iſ. 32.1. c. 33.17.22. Dan. 7.14. Lu. 1.23. Mat. 2.2. c. 21.5. c. 25, 34, 40. Rev. 15.3. c. 17.14. 1 Tim. 15.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt himſelf</hi> in, over his Church, of which they propheſied, ordained <hi>Kings</hi> to be the <hi>chief nurſing Fathers, Protectors,</hi> Pſ. 72.10, 11. Pſ. 138.4. Pſal. 148.11. Iſ. 46.7, 33. c. 60.3, 10, 11, 16. c. 62.2. againſt the ſucceſſively impeached, reſtrained, ſecluded; ſecured Members of both Houſes of Parliament, and the whole Houſe of Lords, not only moſt inſolently and illegally voted down but profeſſedly engaged againſt, by the <hi>Tayle,</hi> of the <hi>garled commons Houſe,</hi> when they had forcibly thruſt out the Majori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of their Fellow-Members, Burgeſſes, which made it no legal <hi>Houſe,</hi> and uſurped to themſelves by a new Self-creation, without a new Election, not only the name of the <hi>Parliament of England,</hi> when they had totally deſtroyed the Parliament it ſelf, but the <hi>Supream Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Nation;</hi> Antichriſtianly<note n="*" place="margin">2 Theſ. 2.4.</note> 
               <hi>exalting themſelves above all that is called God,</hi> or worſhipped, &amp; exerciſing a more tranſcendent lawleſſe boundleſſe Arbitrary power, than any Parliament of King, Lords and Commons, all united in one, ever formerly claimed, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted, both in their <hi>Weſtminſter-Conventicle,</hi> its <hi>ſeveral Committees,</hi> their new <hi>High-courts of Injustice,</hi> their <hi>Counſels of State at White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall,</hi> their City and Country <hi>Sub-committees,</hi> (ſet forth in their proper coulors in the <hi>Hiſtory of Independency,</hi> their own printed new <hi>Knacks, Remonstrances, Engagements, Iohn Lilburnes, Englands</hi> New Chaines his printed, Letter to the <hi>Speaker,</hi> July 6. 1649. and other <hi>Pamphlets.</hi>) In ſo much that after their near five years exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant <hi>Tyranical</hi> Domination, the <hi>very General</hi> and <hi>Officers of the Army,</hi> (by whoſe power, aſſiſtance they undermined, deſtroyed the King, Lords, former Parliament, and conſtituted themſelves alone the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and <hi>Supream Dictators</hi> over our three whole Nations,) by way of juſt <hi>Retaliation,</hi> forcibly diſſolved, ſhamefully thruſt them out of the <hi>Parliament Houſe,</hi> &amp; <hi>Whitehall,</hi> laying their elevated Honor in the duſt; And by their Declaration of <hi>August</hi> 22. 1653. and <hi>A true ſtate of the Common-wealth of England,</hi> 1654. p. 8. &amp;c. not only declared them to be <hi>actually, finally, and juſtly diſſolved from being any
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115471:3"/>more a Parliament, by an extraordinary providence,</hi> &amp; <hi>power;</hi> but alſo branded them to all poſterity, <hi>for a</hi> CORRUPT PAKTY <hi>carrying on their own ends, to perpetuate themſelves in their late,</hi> PARLIAMENTARIE &amp; SV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PREAM AVTHORITIE; <hi>never anſworing the ends which God, his People, and the whole Nation expected from them,</hi> but exerciſing an Arbitrary Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er over <hi>them, likely to ſwallow up all the antient Liberties and Properties of the People, and to perpetuate their Vexations and Oppreſsions in every kind, though the multitude of unneceſſary Laws, and Ordinances, many of which were made upon occaſion of, and to ſuit with the concernments and intereſts of partiaular parties, tending to the abſolute enſlaving of the free-born Nation,</hi> under their perpetual <hi>Dictatorſhip;</hi> as they there at large remonſtrate.</p>
            <p>Theſe New <hi>Athenian Republican Tyrants</hi> (worſe than the worſt of all our Kings) being thus ſodainly diſmounted by the Army, to the general joy and contentment of all three Nations; Generall, and the Army-Officers, ſeating themſelves in the <hi>Supream Power,</hi> (which they alla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies retained and actually exerciſed in reality at their pleaſures, though their <hi>Mock-Porliament</hi> had the <hi>Title</hi> and <hi>viſible</hi> adminiſtration therof) uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped an abſolute <hi>Legiſlative, Tax impoſing, Parliament-modelling, electing, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening, ſecluding, diſſolving power at their pleaſures;</hi> and made their <hi>Genera,</hi> under the Title of <hi>Lord Protector of the</hi> Infant <hi>Common wealth of England Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> (as the <hi>Roman-Souldiers</hi> did their <hi>Generals,</hi> under the' Titles of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> or <hi>Emperour</hi>) a more abſolute real, though not nominal King over us, than any of our antient Kings, and themſelves as a <hi>Counſel of State</hi> and <hi>Major Generals</hi> under him, acted more arbitrarily, tyranically, oppreſſively, as Legiſlators, Military, and civil Dictators, Iudges, or pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Kings under him, than any of our <hi>Saxon</hi> Kings during the <hi>Heptarchy,</hi> or <hi>old Counſel-Table,</hi> Lords, or Lord Lieutenants under our late King, though branded by them as the worſt of Tyrants. Whoſe exorbitant Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities being in ſome meaſure bounded, and their <hi>Major-Generalſhips</hi> ſet aſide by the <hi>Aſſembly</hi> at <hi>Westminſter,</hi> 1657. and their firſt Protector (ſoon after his beloved Daughter) ſodainly out off by unexpected death, and his Son, (no former Officer in the Army) ſucceeding him, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling a New Convention at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> in <hi>Ianuary</hi> 1658. the all-ſwaying <hi>Army-Grandees,</hi> either fearing or diſcerning in him an inclination, rather to cloſe with the antient Nobility, Gentry, Lawyers, and Prebyterians, than with them, and to revive the old <hi>Engliſh Militia</hi> of Trained-bands by degrees for the peoples eaſe in their Taxes, as the probableſt means for, his own and our Nations eaſe, ſettlement, ſecurity; Thereupon they reſolved to ſet up their new <hi>Republick</hi> again: but finding them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and the old and new <hi>Rebublican Members,</hi> (with whom they confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derated) <hi>over-voted in the Houſe by the Lawyers, and Court-party,</hi> in their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of the reviving their former <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> purpoſely to ſet aſide their young Protector, or reduce him and the <hi>Republick</hi> too under their own <hi>priſtine Wardſhip,</hi> they fell to their former <hi>Policy,</hi> whereby they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, diſſolved the long Parliament, ſetting up a new <hi>General Counſel</hi> of <hi>Officers,</hi> and <hi>Agitators of the Army,</hi> againſt their <hi>Protectors</hi> will, and the Votes of thoſe they acknowledged to be the <hi>Parliament, and General Counſel both of England, Scotland, and Ireland,</hi> of both which them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves (like <hi>Ambidexters</hi>) were Members, by which ſtratagem they
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115471:4"/>engaged the major part of the forces here, to ſide with them againſt the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and enforced their <hi>Protector,</hi> by a ſuddain ſurpriſe, much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his will, unexpectedly to diſſolve the Parliament, to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the preſent <hi>Supream Counſel, Dictators,</hi> and <hi>Governors</hi> of our three <hi>Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> as their ſubſequent actions every day more and more demonſtrate.</p>
            <p>To engage all the old and new <hi>Republican Members,</hi> Sectaries, Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers &amp; others in this their foreplotted <hi>New-Confederacy,</hi> they did in ſundry printed papers, at the beginning of the laſt Convention, ſince its diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and in ſeveral <hi>Speeches</hi> in the Houſe, extoll <hi>The Good Old Cauſe</hi> in which they formerly engaged; and what that was, themſelves in ſome of their Speeches, motions for their indemnity and juſtification therein, have diſcovered: to wit, the impeaching and beheading of the late King in an illegal new High Court of Juſtice, againſt the Votes of both Houſes, the Preſidents of all former Ages, the Laws and Statutes of the Land; their own Declarations, Remonſtrances, Commiſsions, Oaths, Vows, Proteſtations, Covenants, yea the very Writs and Indentures by which ſome of them were elected Members of the long Parliament, all obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging them in preciſe terms to <hi>defend the Kings Perſon, Crown,</hi> and <hi>lawfull Authority, (as well as both Houſes of Parliament, their Members, privileges) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst all violence, conſpiracies, and attempts whatſoever.</hi> To diſinherit his royal poſterity, to ſel, divide among themſelves all or moſt of the antient Lands, Rents, Revenues, Treaſure of the Crown, which formerly defrayed the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary expences of the Realm, (without taxing the people) to diſſolve the whole Houſe of Lords, impeach, ſeclude, ſecure, impriſon, &amp; cloſe impriſon the majority of the Houſe of Commons, oppoſite to their new ſpuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Good Cauſe at their pleaſure, and to create the ſmall remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Commons confederated with the Army, an <hi>abſolute Parl. and the Supreme Authority of the Nation, without King or Houſe of Lords,</hi> or the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor part of their ſecluded Fellow-Commoners; to metamorphoſe our <hi>Old Kingdom</hi> into a new Infant <hi>Republick, Oligarchy</hi> under themſelves alone, to diſinherit all ſecluded Members, and other Engliſh Freemen of their hereditary Laws, Liberties, Franchiſes, and put them into a new <hi>Praemunire</hi> without any legal Indictment or Conviction, diſabling them to ſue in any Court, or enjoy, receive any office or preferment whatſoever, unleſs they ſhall perfidiouſly abjure all former Oaths, Proteſtations, Vows, Covenants, and engage to be <hi>true and faithfull to them and their new-minted Republick,</hi> without a <hi>King or Houſe of Lords;</hi> to new-modle our Nations, Parliaments, Government, ſubvert our old fundamental good Laws, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, Properties; impriſon, baniſh, condemn, execute our perſons, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſter, confiſcate our Lands, Offices, real, perſonal Eſtates, ranſack our Houſes, Studies, papers, and create new Treaſons, forfeitures of our Freeholds at their arbitrary Lordly pleaſures: to repeal the Oaths of Supremacy and Allegiance, ſuſpend all penal Executions againſt Jeſuits and Romiſh-Seminaries; give a free toleration, protection to all ſorts of Sects and Religions whatſoever; to hold intimate correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency with Popiſh Princes, Cardinals, Jeſuits, Jeſuited Papiſts, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain juſtifie their moſt abominable, treaſonable principles, as they did in their preceedent, concurrent and ſubſequent to, in and after the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings againſt the King, Members, erection of their new <hi>Free-ſtate,</hi> the worſt of all <hi>Arbitrary Tyranies;</hi> All which &amp; nought elſe but this is the only
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115471:4"/>
               <hi>Good Old Cauſe</hi> they now extoll, &amp; are to act over again, perchance to the ruin or their <hi>late Protectors,</hi> as well as K. <hi>Charles</hi> his poſterity, if they prevail. This their <hi>Good old cauſe,</hi> and <hi>Republike,</hi> is in truth the old pernicious project of Father <hi>Parſons</hi> the Jeſuit, &amp; his confederats, in their <hi>high Court of <hi>&amp; his Memorials for</hi> Reformation for England, <hi>at</hi>
               </hi> Sevil <hi>in</hi> Spain, <hi>An,</hi> 1590 as<note n="(c)" place="margin">In his Quod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libets, p. 92, 94, 95, 233, 286, 305, &amp;c. 306, 307, 308, 330, 332. See my Epiſtle before my Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorical and Legal Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Fundamental Laws, Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties Privileges of all Engliſh Freemen: where all this is largely evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denced: And before my <hi>Jus Patronatus.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Will: Watſon</hi> a ſecular Prieſt at large relates; and of <hi>Tho: Campanella,</hi> an Italian Friar, De Monarchia Hiſpanica, c. 25. p. 204. where he informs the K of <hi>Spain,</hi> 
               <q>That nothing will ſo much conduce to weaken the Engliſh forces, as diſſention &amp; diſcord ſowed amongſt them, &amp; perpetually nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed; which may beſt be effected by theſe 2. means, 1. By in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigating the ſwaying men in the Parliament of <hi>England, <hi>Vt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliam in formam Keipublicae reducant, in imitationem Hollandorum;</hi>
                  </hi> to reduce England into the form of <hi>A Common Wealth,</hi> in imitation of the Hollanders. 2ly, If that could not be effected, then, either by making it an Elective Kingdom; or by ſetting up Kings of another Family, in oppoſition to the true he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditary royal line.</q> To effect which <hi>good old cauſe,</hi> and plot, the Pope, <hi>Parſons,</hi> and other <hi>Jeſuits</hi> engaged the old Gunpowder Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors <hi>to blow up both the King, royal iſſue, Lords and Parliament, Anno</hi> 1605 as the <hi>History of their Arraignment, Speed,</hi> the Statutes of 3 Jac. c. 1, 2, 4, 5. relate: which then proving abortive, the <hi>Pope, Jeſuits,</hi> and Cardinal<note n="(d)" place="margin">Romes Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterpeace.</note> 
               <hi>Richelieu</hi> of France, whiles living, revived, proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this <hi>good cauſe,</hi> to deſtroy our King, Monarchy, and turn it into a Republike, or elſe into an <hi>Elective Kingdom,</hi> to put by K. <hi>Charls</hi> his <hi>progeny;</hi> and<note n="(e)" place="margin">Hiſtoria de Conte Gale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>azzo, Gualdo Priorato. Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, 1648. p. 175, 176.</note> recommended it in writing to the French King, &amp; his Succeſſor Cardinal <hi>Mazarine,</hi> (with whom our Grandees of late years have held intimate correſpondency in proſecution of this <hi>good old cauſe</hi>) vigorouſly to proſecute after his death; who accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly accompliſhed it by the old <hi>Republican Members, and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments own Army,</hi> ſeduced, inſtigated, aſſiſted in it by the <hi>Spaniſh, French</hi> and <hi>Jeſuits Agents. Ol: Cromwell</hi> Pro: himſelf publikely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring in his printed Speech to his Parliament at <hi>Westminſter,</hi> Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temb. 4. 1654: p. 16, 17. <q>That he knew very well, that Emiſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the <hi>Ieſuits</hi> never came over in thoſe ſwarms as they have done ſince theſe things were on foot: and <hi>that divers Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men can bear witneſs with him, that they had a Conſiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry &amp; Counſel abroad that</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Nota bene.</note> 
                  <hi>rules all the Affairs of the things in England:</hi> and had fixed in <hi>England,</hi> in the limits of moſt Cathedrals (of which he was able to produce <hi>the Particular</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Quaere, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of Government, took not its Title thence?</note> 
                  <hi>Inſtrument</hi>) an Epiſcopal power, with Archdeacons, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perſons, to pervert, ſeduce, and deceive the people: yet never capitally executed the penal Lawes againſt any of them.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This being the true Original, progreſs, ſtate, anatomy of this <hi>Good old cauſe,</hi> wherewith the old <hi>Republican Members, Sectaries,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115471:5"/>Army</hi>-Officers, Souldiers, are ſo much enamoured, and ſome would have enforced all Members of the laſt Convention publikely <hi>to justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie and ſubſcribe to, under pain of being ſecluded.</hi> To draw off and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorce their affections, if not henceforth to engage them cordially a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, for their own and the publike good, I ſhall further Anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mize, and paint out the <hi>horrid deformity, and infernal execrableneſs, blackneſs</hi> thereof, by parallelling it with the old <hi>Gunpowder Traytors Plot and Cauſe,</hi> which it farr exceeds in <hi>monſtroſity, exorbitancy, trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery,</hi> and <hi>matchleſs flagitiouſneſs;</hi> though juſtly ſtiled by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Statute of 3 <hi>Jacobi</hi> ch. 2. <hi>The moſt wicked, barbarous, exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable and abominable Treaſon that ever could enter into the heart of most wicked men; and ſuch as was never before heard of:</hi> (though now gilded over with the glorious Title of <hi>The Good Old Cauſe,</hi>) as theſe 8. circumſtances will demonſtrate.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That Good old Cauſe and Treaſon, to deſtroy the King, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, Kingdome was originally<note n="(h)" place="margin">3 Jac. c. 2, 4, 5. Speeds Hiſtory, 3 Jac.</note> contrived in the years 1604. 1605. by Engliſh, Spaniſh Jeſuits, acted by diſcontented Jeſuited Papiſts, abetted by the Pope, and other forein papiſts, all inveterate profeſſed Enemies to our Proteſtant Princes, Parliaments, King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Church, Religion: But thoſe who lately proſecuted, viſibly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in, &amp; actually accompliſhed it, in the years 1647, 1648, 1649, and ſtill purſue it; profeſſe themſelves the moſt zealous Proteſtants, Puritans, Saints, the greateſt Oppoſites to the Roman Pontiff, Church, Religion, Jeſuites, Seminaries and Papiſts, of all others, and the beſt affected people to our <hi>Parliaments</hi> and their privileges.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The old Gunpowder-<hi>Traytors</hi>
               <note n="(i)" place="margin">3 Jac. c. 1, 2, 4, 5, &amp; Speed.</note> contrived that <hi>good old Cauſe, Treaſon beyond the Seas</hi> and in <hi>private ſecret conventicles</hi> here, of none but Jeſuits, Papiſts, obliged by an Oath of Secrecy to conceal it, and were ſo afraid, ſo aſhamed of it, that they purſued it only in the night, acted it under ground in a <hi>dark vault under the Lords Houſe, wherein their train of gunpowder was ſecretly hid with Fagots and other materials.</hi> But thoſe who ſince eſpouſed it, conſulted about, promoted, avowed it in open <hi>General Councils</hi> of the <hi>Army,</hi> and known publike Meetings, Committees of Republican Members of the <hi>Long Parliament, Army,</hi> and others confederating with them, in <hi>England, London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> it ſelf, in the very day-time; and then preſented it in the name of <hi>the Counſil and Army</hi> it ſelf, to the <hi>Parliament Houſe,</hi> at the <hi>Commons barr,</hi> in their <hi>Remonstrance from</hi> St. <hi>Albans</hi> 16 Novemb. 1648 and<note n="(k)" place="margin">The 2. Part of the Hiſtorie of Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency. J Sedg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicks Juſtice on the Armies Remonſtrance</note> other <hi>precedent</hi> and ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent papers; which they printed, divulged in a moſt inſolent manner to all the world.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They plotted, proſecuted their Old cauſe by the <hi>instigation</hi> of the<note n="(l)" place="margin">3 Jac. c. 2, 4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>Pope, Jeſuits,</hi> and <hi>Popiſh Prieſts,</hi> their ghoſtly Fathers, who <hi>confederated with, and encouraged them therein,</hi> and that from the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115471:5"/>
               <note n="(m)" place="margin">Parſons Philopater, §. 2. Treſham de Officio Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipis Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni, c. 5. Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian, Hiſtoria Jeſuitica, l, 3. Ludovicus Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius Hiſt. Jeſ. l. 2. c. 4. Speculu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Jeſuiticum, p. 156, 157. &amp;c.</note> principles of their own <hi>Antichristian, trayterous, bloudy Romiſh Religion; which aſſured them, that it was not only just, lawfull, neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary expedient, but a moſt heroike and meritorious Christian Act, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy, ſubvert, ruin all Protestant Kings, Princes, kingdoms, churches Parliaments, declared by the Pope to be Hereticks, Enemies, or Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks from the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>and aſſure them of a ſaintſhip on Earth, &amp; a crown of glory in heaven for ſuch an heroick attempt.</hi> But thoſe who ſince took up their good old cauſe, 1648. and 1649. and would now revive it, by their inſtigation; did it againſt the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortations of<note n="[n]" place="margin">The 47 Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don Miniſters Petition, Dr. Hamonds Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs, &amp; others</note> 
               <hi>ſundry godly Protestant Ministers,</hi> the<note n="[o]" place="margin">The Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies of Diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience and Rebellion, Deus &amp; Rex, 3 Jac. c. 4. Dr. John Whites Sermon at Pauls Croſs, 1615. &amp; De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Way ch. 6.10. Samuelis Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charti Epiſtola Pariſiis 1650.</note> dehor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of their moſt indeared <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Friends, the Votes of their Fellow Members; the very principles of the Chriſtian and Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion they profeſſed, and publike doctrine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> whereof they were Members; and the Common and Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute Laws of the Realm, all declaring and branding it, as an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernal, Jeſuitical, Popiſh, Antichriſtian practiſe, and moſt deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, matchleſs, High Treaſon, deſerving the higheſt <hi>temporal Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, eternal torments, and condemnation in this and another world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The<note n="(p)" place="margin">3 Jac. c. 12. and Speed.</note> old Popiſh powder Traitors, contrived their treaſon againſt the King and Parliament, meerly out of envy againſt the flouriſhing eſtate, and true profeſſion of the <hi>Protestant Religion</hi> in our 3. Realms under King <hi>James,</hi> the continuing of which happineſs and profeſſion to all poſterity, by reaſon of his moſt hopefull and plentifull Progeny, they much fearing, and maligning; thereupon <hi>moſt horribly and trayterouſly conſpired <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to blow up the King, Queen, Prince, with all the Lords Spiritual &amp; Temporal, and Commons, when aſſembled in the Upper Houſe of Parliament,</hi> Nov. 5. 1605. <hi>pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely concluding to do it in that Houſe, that where ſundry neceſſary and religious Laws for the preſervation of the Church and State were made, (which they falſly and ſlanderouſly termed</hi> Cruel Laws) &amp; enacted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them and their Religion; <hi>both place and perſons ſhould be all deſtroyed and blown up at once; which would have turned to the utter ruine of the whole kingdom, and ſubverſion of the whole State,</hi> had it been effected: But the Republican Members, Army-Officers, and chief Actors in this new <hi>Good old cauſe,</hi> had no ſuch inducements, to engage them againſt the King, his royal iſſue, the true Proteſtant Religion, Parliament or kingdom of <hi>England;</hi> whoſe flouriſhing eſtate, welfare, proſperity ſafety, and defence againſt theſe Romiſh Enemies forces, conſpiracies, and the making, executing of new ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verer Lawes againſt them paſſed by both Houſes, and aſſented to by the King in the laſt Treaty: were the principal things they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended they contended and fought for, in all their printed Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrances, Declarations proteſtations, and Solemn League and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant:
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115471:6"/>as the printed <hi>Collections</hi> of both Houſes &amp; the <hi>Armies</hi> Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations irrefragably manifeſt: And ſo moſt powerfull arguments to diſwade them from, and engage them againſt this their <hi>Good old cauſe;</hi> which yet notwitſtanding they wilfully proſecuted, to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter overthrow and ſubverſion of the late <hi>King, kingdom, Parliament, Houſe of Peers,</hi> which they quite blew up; the <hi>Royal poſterity,</hi> and thereby the Church of <hi>England</hi> and Proteſtant Religion (much ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalized, defamed by it) in a great meaſure.</p>
            <p n="5">5. All thoſe who lately engaged in this good old cauſe, were Members of Parliament, or of the Parliaments Army, commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. raiſed, payed,<note n="(q)" place="margin">Exact Coll. p. 339, 340, 342, 456, 457 932. A Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, p. 43, 44, 305, 406. to 430, 598, 606, 623, 668, 669.</note> obliged by their Writs and Indentures of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, their Oaths of Supremacy, Fealty, Allegiance, Proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Vow, Covenant, League, with their manifold Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Remonſtrances, which they all made as Members of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or the Army, and other ſacred and civil obligations inviolably to preſerve, defend the Kings perſon, crown, dignity, poſteritie, the kingdom, Church of <hi>England,</hi> the Parl. with its Members, privileges, the fundamental Laws, Liberties, and Government of the Nation: who yet notwithſtaning moſt perfidiouſly, treacherouſly, atheiſtically, ſubverted and deſtroyed them all one after another, contrary to all theſe moſt ſacred multiplied oathes, and ſtricteſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations, beyond all preſidents of the worſt and moſt treacherous Monſters ſince the creation; whereas all the Gunpowder Traitors, (as the<note n="(r)" place="margin">Lud. Lucius &amp; Hoſpinian, Hiſt. Jeſuitica, l. 3. p. 204 l. 4. p. 264. Speeds Hiſtory.</note> 
               <hi>Jeſuits by their Oaths, the rules of their Order, the commands of their Superiors; the reſt by a particular Oath;</hi> Guy Faux, the Low-country Souldier who was to ſet fire to the train, and others) were purpoſely hired, employd thus to blow up, deſtroy our old King, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, Religion, kingdom, and had no ſuch obligations, oaths to reſtrain them from it, as theſe New conſpirators had; which ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravates their <hi>Guilt,</hi> and makes them ten thouſand fold worſe, yea more execrable to God and all good men, than they.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The Gunpowder Traytors, had their plot taken effect, were yet ſo aſhamed of it, yea ſo farr from juſtifying or owning it <hi>as a good old cauſe;</hi>
               <note n="(ſ)" place="margin">Speeds Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory, p. 1241. The Arraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors.</note> 
               <hi>that they agreed before-hand, to caſt the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation thereof <hi>on the Puritans,</hi> to make them more odious:</hi> And ſome Jeſuits and Papiſts ſoon after publiſhed in ſundry Books, <q>
                  <note n="(t)" place="margin">Ludovicus Lucius Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoria Jeſuitica l. 2. c. 4. p. 208, 209.</note> that there was no ſuch plot as this really contrived by them, but that it was a feigned plot deviſed by the Puritans, to render them and their Religion infamous and odious to all poſterity.</q> Yea the Jeſuits of <hi>Colen</hi> moſt impudently aſſerted; <q>that this Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powder Treaſon was plotted only by the Calviniſts, and not by any Catholick; that no Jeſuit had any hand in, or knowledge of it; and that <hi>Henry Garnet</hi> the Jeſuit, was only executed for his Religion, not for this horrid Treaſon, of which he was not found
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115471:6"/>guilty,</q> as<note n="(u)" place="margin">Andreas Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demon, Johan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, Apologia pro Henrico Garneto,</note> 
               <hi>Endaemon Johannis,</hi> and<note n="(x)" place="margin">Opus Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nographicum totius Orbis p. 309.</note> 
               <hi>Laurentius Beyerlincke,</hi> moſt falſly publiſhed to the world, againſt the Indictment, Verdict, Evidence and Iudgement againſt him, by which he was moſt clearly found guilty thereof: But thoſe Republican Saints, Zealots, and over-grown Puritans, who lately proſecuted their <hi>good old Gunpowder plot and cauſe,</hi> executing far more than they durſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; are ſo farr from being aſhamed of, diſowning, abominating this moſt execrable, impious, treacherous, monſtrous powder trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; and that after<note n="y" place="margin">3 Jac. c. 1, 2, 4, 5, 7. Jac. c, 4, 6.</note> ſundry Acts of Parliament, Proclamations, Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories, Treatiſes, publike annual ſolemn thankſgivings, and thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of excellent Sermons preached, printed on the Fifth of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember</hi> for above 40 years ſpace, (yet continued in moſt places, and ſtill obſerved by many of themſelves) ſetting forth the matchleſs, devilliſh, infernal, monſtrous barbarouſneſs, of that old abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Treaſon; the tranſcendent Treachery, Execrableneſs of thoſe unnatural Traitors, and the odiouſneſs of that <hi>Antichristian Religion (whoſe Faith is but meer faction, rebellion, &amp; whoſe practice is the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring of ſouls &amp; bodies)</hi> that engaged them therin, to their everlaſting<note n="*" place="margin">3 Jac. c. 1.</note> infamy, by a ſpecial Act of Parliament, that ſo it and our thankfull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for being delivered from it, may <hi>never be forgotten, but had in perpetual Remembrance in all ages to come.</hi> Yea after all theſe old Traitors exemplary condemnations, forfeitures execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and hanging up of their Heads, Quarters, over both Houſes of Parl. to deter all others from the like treaſonable attempts. That though this their late plot was for certain<note n="(a)" place="margin">The 2. part of the Hiſtory of Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency, my E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to a Seaſonable, legal &amp; hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, My Speech in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, p. 107 &amp; the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendix to it.</note> originally projected &amp; infuſed into them by <hi>Jeſuites</hi> and <hi>Popiſh</hi> Agents, yet they openly attributed to themſelves both the projecting, proſecution, accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of this tranſcendent <hi>Treaſon,</hi> farr exceeding theirs, and proclaimed, juſtified it in ſundry of their <hi>Remonstrances, Ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, Papers,</hi> as a moſt <hi>heroick, Saint</hi>-like <hi>Chriſtian, Honorable, and meritorious Act of Justice, wherein God himſelf hath moſt gloriouſly appeered, bearing witneſs to, and owning it from Heaven, by their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paralleld ſucceſſes,</hi> not only as a <hi>Good,</hi> but the <hi>very beſt of cauſes, tending to the great advancement of the Throne and kingdom of the Lord Ieſus Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ist;</hi> Some of them deſiring that the everlaſting me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of it may be inſcribed on their <hi>publike Statues,</hi> or <hi>Monuments</hi> For their eternal honour in all ſucceeding Generations: Whereas the very fouleſt Devils, and worſt of damned <hi>Spirits in Hell,</hi> would be both afraid, aſhamed to own or approve ſuch an infernal black cauſe as this, much leſs to juſtifie and extoll it in ſuch a prodigious impudent manner, as ſome now doe, which exceedingly heightens and aggravates their Impudency, Impenitency, Guilt, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation. Certainly thoſe muſt have<note n="(b)" place="margin">Jer. 3.3.</note> 
               <hi>wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>riſh forheads, brows of braſs, hearts of steel,</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">2 Tim. 4.2.</note> and <hi>conſeiences ſeared with an hot iron,</hi> who
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115471:7"/>dare to own, extoll, or eſpouſe ſuch a prodigy, or Cauſe as this. And may doe well to remember thoſe two woes, which will fall upon them for it, Iſa. 5.18.20. <hi>Wo unto them that draw Iniquity with cords of vanity, and ſin as with a cartrope. Wo unto them that call <hi>Evil</hi>
               </hi> (yea the worſt of all Evils, Treaſons) <hi>
                  <hi>Good,</hi> and good will, that put darkneſs for light, and light for darkneſs; that put bitter for ſweet, and ſweet for bitter;</hi> and now call the deſtruction of their law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Soveraign, their Native Country, kingdom, Church, the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments of <hi>England</hi> and their privileges, their <hi>Good Old cauſe,</hi> and<note n="(d)" place="margin">Phil. 3.19.</note> 
               <hi>glory in theſe their ſhamefull Actions;</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Job. 42, 6.</note> which ſhould cauſe them <hi>rather to abhor themſelves, and repent in dust and aſhes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7ly. The old Gunpowder Traitors only plotted, but never actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally effected the blowing up of the King, Parliament, and Houſe of Lords, thorugh the <hi>providence</hi> of<note n="f" place="margin">3 Jac. c. 1.</note> Almighty God, who in all ages hath ſhewed his power and mercy in the miraculous and gratious deliverance of his church, and in the protection of Religious Kings and States. But our new <hi>Salt-peter-men,</hi> have with an high ſtorng hand fully executed,<note n="g" place="margin">See their Declaration of 17 March, 1648. &amp; May 6. 1659. John Godwins Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructors of Juſtice, Cooks &amp; Bradſhawes Speeches, John Miltons Anſwer to Salmatius, and ſundry other printed Pamphlets.</note> accompliſhed whatever they deſigned; and becauſe they miſcarried not in it, like them, but by Gods juſtice up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, us, our King, Lords, Parliament for all our crying ſins, have proſpered in this <hi>Foelix Seelus,</hi> and brought their <hi>wicked devices to paſs;</hi> they glory in it, as the <hi>Higheſt Act of Juſtice,</hi> the <hi>
                  <hi>Beſt of Cauſes;</hi> the Greateſt Mercy and Deliverance that ever befell</hi> the Engliſh Nation; point blank againſt the<note n="(h)" place="margin">Pſal. 37, 1.7. Pſ. 73.3, &amp;c. Pſ. 92.6, 7. Pſ. 94.3, 4, 5. Dan. 11.33.36 Mat. 7.21. Acts 2.33. Pro. 29.19, 20, 21, 22, 23. Job 21.7. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of <hi>Chriſtian Religion:</hi> whereby they have involved us in many inteſtine and forein Wars with our <hi>Protestant Brethren</hi> and <hi>Allies,</hi> by <hi>Sea</hi> and <hi>Land,</hi> which they have dyed red and drenchd with precious Chriſtian bloud; exhauſted our publike treaſures, deſtroyed our trade, impoveriſhed, oppreſſed, quite eaten out the wealth and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of our Nation; impoſed endleſſe Egyptian burdens on their backs, an Iron Yoak of vaſſallage on their necks; ſubverted all Liberty, property, unity, amity, real piety, charity, honeſty, juſtice; divided us into ſundry irreconcileable Sects, ſchiſms, factions, fractions; perplexed us with ſundry manifold fears, dangers, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain changes, alterations, diſſolutions of Government, Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſupreme and ſubordinate Authorities, yea reduced us into a deſperate, unſetled, floating, tottering condition, without any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable means or hopes of the leaſt ſetled eſtabliſhment, and brought that ſevere judgement which God threatned to, and inflicted on the <hi>Rebellious</hi> ten tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> (who revolted from, and rebelled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their lawfull Soveraign, and right heir to the Houſe of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> King <hi>Rehoboam;</hi>
               <note n="(i)" place="margin">Hoſea 8.4. c. 13.11.</note> 
               <hi>ſetting up Kings, but not by God, and making them Princes,</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Hoſea 3.4.</note> 
               <hi>and he knew it not, whom God took away in his wrath?)
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115471:7"/>The children of Iſrael ſhall abide many days, <hi>without a King, and without a Prince, &amp;c.</hi>
               </hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Hoſea 10.2, 3, 4. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>He hath divided their heart, now ſhall they be found faulty: For now they ſhall ſay</hi> (and I wiſh we all would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider it &amp; ſay ſo too) <hi>We have no King,</hi> (no true Parliament nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) <hi>becauſe we feared not the Lord: <hi>What then ſhould</hi> a King</hi> (or Parliament) <hi>do to us?</hi> (to help us in our confuſions and extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities.) <hi>They have ſpoken lying words ſwearing falſly in making <hi>a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant;</hi> thus judgement ſpringeth up as hemlock in the furrows of the field:</hi> (one Judgement of God, one trouble, war, change, confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, oppreſſion upon the neck of another, and many complicated Judgements together) <hi>So that</hi> Iſrael <hi>ſhall be aſhamed of his own counſel; now her King is cut off, as the fome upon the water;</hi> and the High places (wherein they ſeated themſelves) deſtroyed; and all their New Modles of Goverments, Parliaments deſtroyed by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; they being now diſuniting, undermining one another more than ever; never free from new Troubles, plots, fears, jealouſies, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexities, ſince they undertook this New <hi>Good Old Romiſh Cauſe;</hi> blow up <hi>King, Lords, Parliaments;</hi> ſince they <note n="m" place="margin">1 Kings 21, 19.</note> 
               <hi>killed, and alſo took poſſeſsion;</hi> and like thoſe rebellious <hi>wicked H. ſbandmen</hi> in the<note n="n" place="margin">Mat. 21.38.39. 1. u. 19.27 c. 20.14, 15, 16.</note> 
               <hi>Gospel ſaid among themſelves (when the ſon came to dem and the fruits of his Fathors vineyard from them, and caſt him out of the vineyard) this is <hi>the Heir, Come let us kill him, and ſeiſe upon the Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and it ſhall be ours:</hi>
               </hi> which ended in the <hi>miſerable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of thoſe wicked men, <hi>and taking away their uſurped vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, which was let out to other Husbandmen, who would render the fruits thereof in due ſeaſon.</hi>
               </hi> All which conſidered, our new Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der mens Guilt, crime as far tranſcends the old Powder Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, as actual Murder, deſtruction of the King, Parliament, king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Laws, Liberties, and ill conſequents thereof, exceed only in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentionall, without effect: Theirs unſetled nothing, and did no miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief to the publike: whereas their actual accompliſhment of their old plot, hath brought actual deſtruction on them all, and endleſſe miſeries, diſtractions ever ſince to our Three whole Nations, Churches, and God only knows, not man, what ſodain and final ruine it may bring upon them all. And is it then a <hi>good old cauſe</hi> as they now proclaim it to all the world afreſh <hi>May</hi> 7. 1659?</p>
            <p n="8">8ly. The Gunpowder Traytors engaged in their pretended <hi>Good old Cauſe,</hi> never paſſed any ſolemn Iudgement and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation againſt it, before or after its undertaking, which thoſe who eſpouſed this new miſnamed <hi>Good old cauſe</hi> have often done, againſt it, themſelves, and all ſuch who appeared in it. Not to preſs or inſiſt upon the antient Reſolutions, Statutes of 4 E. 3. rot. parl.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115471:8"/>n. 1. 25 E. 3. c. 2.21 R. 2. c. 22. 1 H. 4. c. 10.31 H. 6. c 1. i E. 6. c. 12. 3 Jac. c. 1, 2, 4, 5. poſitively declaring, reſolving, <hi>the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vying of war againſt the King or Parliament, the plotting, compaſsing the death or destruction of either of them by any open Acts, to be High-Treaſon.</hi> The Republican Members of the long Parliament and Army did together with the reſt of the members, in ſundry Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, reſolve, declare, [particularly in the<note n="o" place="margin">Exact Coll. p. 576.</note> Declaration of the Lords and Commons aſſembled in Parliament, printed and publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by their ſpecial Order, <hi>August</hi> 8. 1642. to the end <hi>that no man might be miſled through ignorance:) That all ſuch perſons who ſhall up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any pretence whatſoever, aſsiſt the King in making war againſt the <hi>Parliament,</hi> with Horſe, arms, plate or money, <hi>are Traytors to His Maieſty, the Parliament, and the Kingdom,</hi> and ſhall be brought to condign puniſhment for ſo high an Offence.</hi> Upon which ground alone, the Lords and Commons by their Ordinance of <hi>Apr.</hi> 1.1643 ſequeſtred the eſtates of all <hi>ſuch perſons, Eccleſiastical or Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral, <hi>as Traytors and Notorious Delinquents,</hi> who have rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed or ſhall raiſe Armes <hi>againſt the Parliament;</hi>
               </hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">A Collection of Ordinances p. 13. 219, 220.</note> 
               <hi>or have been, are, or ſhall be in actual Arms againſt the ſame; or have contributed, or ſhall contribute voluntarily, any money, plate, horſe, arms, ammunition, or other ayde or aſsiſtance, for or towards the maintenance of any forces rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>againſt the Parliament,</hi> and of all ſuch as have joyned <hi>or ſhall joyn in any Oath, or Act of Aſſociation againſt the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> or have impoſed or ſhall impoſe any Tax or Aſſeſſment upon his Majeſties ſubjects, For or towards the maintenance of any forces <hi>againſt the Parliament.</hi>
               </hi> Upon this only ground they afterwards con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, executed Mr. <hi>Tomkins</hi> and Mr. <hi>Chaloner</hi> in the year 1643. as Traitors, for receiving a Commiſſion from the late <hi>King</hi> dated<note n="h" place="margin">A Collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, p. 199, 200 201.</note> 
               <hi>March</hi> 16. <hi>An.</hi> 18 <hi>Caroli,</hi> to raiſe <hi>forces in &amp; about</hi> London <hi>to force the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and ſeiſe upon ſome of the principal Members of it,</hi> though they never put it in actual execution, nor offered the leaſt force to the Parliament, to either of the houſes, or their Members. Since which ſundry others were elſewhere condemned and execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as Traitors, upon the ſame account of <hi>levying war against the Parliament.</hi> Yea, both<note n="i" place="margin">A Collection p. 905, 906, 907, 908.</note> Houſes in their laſt <hi>Propoſitions to the King,</hi> exempted ſome particular perſons <hi>fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any pardon for their lives or eſtates, perpetually baniſhed and confiſcated the eſtates of others,</hi> and put all the reſt to great Fines, only <hi>for levying warr againſt the Parliament,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See the 2. part of the Hiſtory of Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency.</note> which they declared to be <hi>High Treaſon.</hi> Yea the Republican members ſitting after the others ſecluſion, and Army-Officers themſelves in their late <hi>High courts of Juſtice,</hi> impea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, condemned, beheaded our late King * <hi>Charls</hi> himſelf, the Head
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115471:8"/>of the Parliament, the Marqueſs of <hi>Hamilton,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Holland,</hi> the Lord <hi>Capel,</hi> others of the Lords Houſe, and divers Commoners; and condemned, executed Sir <hi>Charles Lucas</hi> with others, in and by a bare Councel of War at <hi>Colchester,</hi> confiſcating moſt of their real and perſonal eſtates, <hi>as Rebells, Traytors, and publike Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,</hi> only for levying <hi>war, and taking up Arms against both Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Parliament.</hi> Since which, the <hi>Army-Officers,</hi> and thoſe in late yea preſent power, in and by their <hi>Inſtrument of Government,</hi> 1653. and contradictory <hi>Humble Petition and Advice,</hi> 1657. diſabled all perſons <hi>who had formerly taken up arms and levied any war against the Parliament, at any time ſince the year</hi> 1641. <hi>and given no ſignal teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of their good affection to the Parliament in taking up Arms for its defence; to be diſabled to be choſen Members of Parliament, or to give their voice in the election of any ſuch Members:</hi> Yet neither the King himſelf, nor any of all theſe beheaded, execcuted, excepted, ſequeſtred, diſabled Lords, Citizens, Souldiers, Gentlemen, ever actually aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted the Parliament it ſelf, or either of the Houſes of Parliament, or any Member or Members thereof, ſitting in, entring into, or returning from the Houſes; nor ſecured, ſecluded, them by any Gards put upon the Houſes, only for ſpeaking their Conſciences, or <hi>diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging their duties in the Parliament,</hi> as they did; but only waged war againſt the Parliament and Members thereof at a great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, by levying war againſt the forces raiſed by them: neither did the King or his Forces in any of their Proclamations or Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations ever affirm, that they took up arms againſt the Parliament it ſelf, or its Members, to diſſolve, ſecure, ſeclude, force or interrupt their proceeding;<note n="k" place="margin">An Exact Coll. p. 349, 350, 351, to 357. 451, 455, 470, 472, 620, 621.</note> 
               <hi>which they utterly diſclaimed,</hi> but only to defend <hi>the Kings perſon, his just Royal authority, and thoſe adhering to him, against the Parliament Army; to preſerve and maintain the just Power, Rights, privileges of Parliament, and the loyal Members therein, the Laws of the Land, the Liberty and Property of the Subjects,</hi> againſt the uſurpations of a prevailing <hi>Faction,</hi> who had (as they affirmed) rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſod Forces to deſtroy the <hi>King, Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rchy it ſelf, the very Freedom, Rights and Privileges of Parliament, and the Liberty, Property of the Subjects;</hi> which they conſtantly aſſerted in all their printed Papers to the very end of the War. If they then not withſtanding all this were thus capitally and criminally proceeded againſt, ſentenced, executed, ſequeſtred, diſabled, by the Votes, Reſolutions, Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Inſtrument, Declarations of the Republica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Members, Officers, Soldiers themſelves, now crying up this <hi>Good old cauſe, <hi>as Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and publike Enemies;</hi>
               </hi> for levying war againſt the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment only thus <hi>mediately, indirectly, conſequentially,</hi> and <hi>ſecundarily,</hi> becauſe they waged war againſt the forces raiſed for the Parliaments defence and ſafeguard: and if the unarmed <hi>London Apprentices,</hi> and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115471:9"/>other diſorderly perſons coming unarmed to the Commons Houſe dores, and there in a tumultuous manner, preſſing ſome Members to <hi>paſs a Petition,</hi> and ſome <hi>Votes</hi> they deſired, without ſeiſing, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing or ſecluding any one Member of either Houſe; though an unarmed force; was preſently ſo reſented by the General and Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the <hi>Army,</hi> that they immediaty declared it to be a<note n="l" place="margin">The Generals Letter from Bedford, 30 July 1647. &amp; His and the Armies Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance 8. Auguſt 1647.</note> 
               <hi>
                  <hi>Treaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable act and force,</hi> for which they preſſed speedy exemplary Juſtice to be executed againſt the chief Actors in, and abettors of it, to prevent the like attempts and force for the future.</hi> Then doubtleſs, by all theſe Judgements and Reſolutions, the Martching up of the Officers and Soldiers of the very Parliaments own Army, (purpoſely raiſed by themſelves for their defence againſt all force and violence whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver offered unto them as Members) in an hoſtile manner; againſt their Duties, Truſts, Commiſſions, proteſtations, Covenants, both Houſes Votes Orders, and expreſs commands, ſeveral times one after another; to impeach ſecure, ſeclude, impriſon eject what Members of the Lords and Commons Houſe they pleaſed; to garble purge the houſes themſelves; to enforce them to repeal their former Votes, Orders, Odinances; their bringing up the whole Army to <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Westminſter,</hi> againſt the Houſes commands, removing their very Guards out of their Quarters; their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible taking the kings perſon out of the cuſtody of the Committee of Parliament, and diſpoſing of him as they pleaſed, contrary to both Houſes direction; their ſecuring and impriſoning above 40 Members, and ſecluding above 100 more at once, by whole Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments of Horſe and Foot, beſetting all paſſages to the Houſes: Their ſuppreſſing the <hi>whoſe Houſe of Lords</hi> and ſetting Guards up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſmall remainder of the Commons Houſe, to force them to vote and un-vote what they pleaſed; their beheading the King, the Head of the Parliament, and ſundry Proteſtant Lords (but not one Popiſh Lord, Brieſt, Ieſuite, though <hi>the principal Incendiaries and promoters of theſe wars, and ſo</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Exact Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection p. 816, 817, 819, 826, 827, 662, 438, 662, 664, 664, 666, 336, 637, 637, 907 to 916. A Collect. p. 218, 227, 240, 704, 705, 706.</note> 
               <hi>declared by both Houſes</hi>) who were Members of the Lords Houſe againſt the Houſes votes, in ſtrange High Courts of Iuſtice, which they forcibly ſet up; their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving the Parliament it ſelf by force, againſt an expreſſe Act of Parliament (to omit the like force ſince upon ſome of their own cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated <hi>Mock-Parliaments,</hi> tranſcending all preſidents of former ages) and ſecluding mcſelf and other Members afreſh, <hi>May</hi> 7. 1659. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to all their Obligations, Truſts; muſt needs be a more Capital Treaſon in all reſpects, than the bare ſucceſſeleſs plot of the old <hi>Guno powder Traytors;</hi> and a more treaſonable, actual levying war againſt the Parl. it ſelf, than the late beheaded kings, Lords or any ſequeſtred diſabled Cavahers, for which they deſerve all the capital Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, execution, penalties, forfeitures, ſequeſtrations and diſabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115471:9"/>for ever to elect, or to be elected Members in any ſuture Parliament; which they and their Confederates have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced againſt others; for farr leſſer Offences, and not ſo direct and profeſſed Wars immediately againſt the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it ſelf and its Member, as themſelves are by their own Declarations, Remonſtrances, and printed Papers, moſt real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly guilty of in a farr higher degree than the late King, or any Cavaliers, &amp; ſtill impenitently juſtifie, applaud, perſiſt in with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt remorſe, and now ſtile, their Good Old Cauſe.</p>
            <p>I ſhall therefore earneſtly deſire all perſons ingaged in this <hi>whoriſh, baſtard old Cauſe,</hi> now ſeriouſly and ſadly to conſider, how their often forcing Ruptures, of the houſes, Members, privileges of Parliament; their abſurd, frequent new-modelling of our Government, Parliaments, according to their own whymſical fancies, preſent intereſts and deſigns, carried on <hi>with prayers, mock-faſts, and humiliations, for ſtrife and debate, and to ſmite with the fiſt of wickedneſſe,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 58.2, 3, 4, 5, &amp;c. c. 1.10. to 24. c. 66.3.4.</note> 
               <hi>most execrable unto God,</hi> have produced theſe deplorable effects.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A juſtification and verification of all the late Kings <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations, Proclamations, Prophetical predictions, grounds, reaſons, fears:</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Exact Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, 618, 657, 658 893 895, 320, 325, 322. A collection, p. 28, 38, 39, 116, 117.</note> 
               <hi>That this Army was raiſed by a factious, ambitious, prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing party in the Houſes of Parliament (whatever they pretended to the contrary) to depoſe, murder, and deſtroy the Kings perſon, life, Crown, dignity, posterity, and Monarchy it ſelf; the whole frame of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment both in Church and State; the Rights, Privileges and Freedom of Engliſh Parliaments, to ſubvert the true eſtabliſhed Proteſtant Religion; the Law of the Land, the Properties, Laws and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Subject; to introduce Democracy and Parity; and ſubject them all to an Arbitrary, Military and Tyrannical power of <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts, Browniſts, and of a few Seditious, Factious, Covetous and Ambitious perſons;</hi> who by being ſeized of all the Armes, Ships, and ſtrong places of the kingdom, (if they ſhould happen to prevail in this war againſt his Majeſty,) <hi>would in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpite not only of the people, but of their preſent Rulers,</hi> (if they ſhould be willing to divert them) <hi>extirpate the Law rent and branch, alter the whale Frame of Government, introduce Democracy, Independency, Parity and leave neither King, Church, Lord nor Gentleman:</hi> distinguiſh between
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115471:10"/>thoſe who aſſiſted them but a little, not out of zeal and out of fear, and thoſe now called <hi>Moderate man,</hi> they will then call <hi>Malignant,</hi> and the Inequality, Injuſtice and Oppreſſion they will then indure, will too late diſcover to them to their coſts; <hi>That they have undone themſelves with too much Diſcretion,</hi> and obtained nothing by <hi>their unjuſtifiable cautious Compliance,</hi> but <hi>to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed laſt.</hi>
               </hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Exact Coll. p. 320, 321, 322.</note> 
               <hi>And by this means the moſt excellent Constitution of our Government, moulded out of a mixture of the three kinds of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment amongst men,</hi> Abſolute Monarchy, Ariſtocracy <hi>and</hi> Democracy, <hi>by</hi> the experience and wiſdom of our <hi>Ancestors, to give to this Kingdom (ſo farr as humane prudence can provide) the conveniences of all 3, without the inconveniences of any one of them, as long as the ballance runs even between them, and they run joyntly in their proper channels; (which bath made this Nation for many years both famous and happy, even to a great degree of envy;) ſhall by this means <hi>end in a dark equal Chanos or confuſion;</hi> and the <hi>long Line of our Noble Anceſtors,</hi> end in a <hi>Iack Cade,</hi> or a <hi>Wat Tyler.</hi>
               </hi> Upon which reaſons alone the King profeſſed he took up arms, for his own neceſſary defence, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of all theſe predicted miſchieſs, now really and truly accompliſhed in every point, worthy our ſaddeſt contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plations. 2ly. It hath produced a falſification of all the long Parliaments and Armies Declarations, Remonſtrances, Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtations, Vows, Covenants, to the contrary, in anſwer, or oppoſition to the Kings Declarations and Proclamations. 3ly. A tranſlation from the Kings and his parties heads, ſouls, upon the Armies and ſome of the late Parliaments heads, ſouls the guilt of all that Chriſtian bloud, ſhed in our inteſtin wars againſt the King and his party, by turning their pretended juſt defenſive, into an unlawfull, offenſive, invaſive, deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive war againſt their lawfull King &amp; Parliament too. 4ly. A juſtification, or extenuation of the Popes, Jeſuits, and papiſts moſt treaſonable, Poſitions, principles, Conſpiracies, Practiſes, Regicides, Powder-plots, againſt our Proteſtant Princes, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, Kingdom, Church, Religion, &amp; other forein Kings, Churches, States, now exceeded by them. 5ly, An inexpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſcandal, infamy, to the profeſsion, &amp; zealous Profeſſors of the Proteſtant Religion, as now more treacherous, perfidious,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115471:10"/>diſloyal, ſeditious, covetous, rebellious, bloody, hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critical, faithleſſe, apoſtatical, diabolical, atheiſtical, than the worſt of Papiſts, Pagans, Turks, Infidels. 6ly. A baſe contempt, ſcorn, deriſion, infamy, diſhonour even of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments themſelves, their luriſdiction, Privileges, Members, Proceedings, Votes, Ordinances, quite trampled under feet, and made the ſong and by-word of every common Souldier, Sculler, Fidler, Drunkard. 7ly. A perpetual diſhonour, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquy, diſgrace upon the whole Engliſh Nation, in all fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rein States, Countries, Kingdoms, who now ſcorn us as the moſt ſlaviſh, ſottiſh, unfaithfull, unpolitick, unprovident, vileſt, perverſeſt, fooliſheſt, variableſt Nation under Heaven. 8ly. An indeliable infamy upon the very profeſſion of a Souldier, and whole Parliament Army, who have verified this old Adage to the uttermoſt,
<q>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Lucan.</note> Nulla fides pietaſve viris qui caſtra ſequntur.</q> 9ly. A preſent incomparable dearth and loſſe of all ſorts of Trade, Traffique by Land or Sea; a preſent confuſion, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſettlement in our Government, Counſils, and all publick Affairs; a general diſcontent, fear, diſpondency in all ſorts of people, a greater fraction, diſ-union of all dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick publick intereſts, and ſtricter combination of our forein Enemies againſt us to work our ruine and wreck their malice and revenge upon us, than ever heretofore. 10ly. A freſh occaſion and advantage to all our Popiſh Adverſaries, not only to traduce, deride, reproach, blaſpheme our Proteſtant Profeſſion and Religion, as<note n="*" place="margin">Milliere his victory of Truth. 1654.</note> ſome of them have done in print, as a mere Seminary of Treaſon, Rebellion, Sedition, Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, perjury, Diſloyalty, and all ſorts of Villany: but to combine together in a holy League, to<note n="*" place="margin">Hoſpinian Jeſuit. l. 2. p. 213, 214, 215. Lud. Lucius Hiſt. Jeſuitica, l. 2. c. 2. p. 186, 187, 188 &amp; l. 4 c. 1. p. 346.</note> extirpate it and all profeſſors of it out of the World, now thus divided from, engaged againſt each other, exhauſted, weakned, diſ-united from eachother, and almoſt totally ruined one by another, through their long inteſtine bloody wars, feuds, and infinite Sects, Factions, endeavouring to undermine, weaken, deſtroy, and not daring to truſt each other.<note n="(b)" place="margin">Mat. 12.25.</note> A <hi>very ſad preſage, or fore-runner of our approaching ruine;</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">Lucan, lib. 1.</note> 
               <hi>En que diſcordia Cives porduxit miſeros?</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Lam. 2.13.</note> 
               <hi>What ſhall I equal unto
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115471:11"/>thee, O Virgin Daughter of our diſtracted</hi> Engliſh Zion, <hi>that I might comfort thee? for thy breach is great like the Sea, who can heal thee?</hi> O that the ſerious conſideration of all theſe deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable effects, might now at laſt effectually work upon the iron, ſteeled hearts, the intoxicated brains, ſeared conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, rebellious ſpirits, perverſe wills, reprobate ſenſes, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly paſſions, ſelf-ſeeking affections of all Army-Officers, Souldiers, Republicans, Sectaries, and others heretofore or now engaged in the purſute of this <hi>Good Old Cauſe,</hi> to bring them to a ſpeedy repentance of all the evils they have acted, occaſioned by and under the ſpecious mask of <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, Juſtice, Liberty, Zeal, Neceſsity, Publick ſafety, Self-preſervation, the ſetting up Christs Kingdom, propagating the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, reformation of Abuſes, and maintaining their</hi> Good Old Cauſe. And that this <hi>Anatomy</hi> of their <hi>Good Old Cauſe,</hi> (the principle end of its publication.) according to their freſh printed<note n="*" place="margin">Miſdated <hi>April</hi> 6. for <hi>May</hi> 6. being made in haſt.</note> Declaration, <hi>May</hi> 6. 1659. <hi>might lead them to look back and examine the true cauſe of the Lords late withdrawing his wonted preſence,</hi> and GOOD SPIRIT (which formerly appeared among them) <hi>from them, and where they firſt turned out of the way;</hi> (in forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king their firſt eſpouſed <hi>Good Old Cauſe,</hi> to commit Whorcdom with the <hi>old whore of Romes cauſe</hi>) their many <hi>back-ſlidings from which,</hi> by wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring divers wayes FROM RIGHTEOUS AND EQUAL PATHS; hath (as themſelves ingenuouſly confeſſe) put <hi>the Publick concernments of this Common wealth, through a Viciſsitude of dangers, into that ſad unſetled ſtate and poſture wherein they now stand, and rendred all their eſſaies to obviate the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and to ſettle theſe Nations in peace and proſperity utterly ineffectual, the only wiſe God in the courſe of his providence diſappointing all their endeavours therein:</hi> ſince they ſecured, ſecluded the old honeſt <hi>members</hi> and Houſe of Lords, from the exerciſe and diſcharge of their truſts, and owned their new <hi>Old Cauſe,</hi> and purged <hi>Republican Conventicle,</hi> for the only Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, without their <hi>Fellow-Members, King, or Houſe of Lords</hi> whom they now call in again againſt their former <hi>Declaration</hi> upon which they caſe them out.</p>
            <p>It ſhall be my prayer to God, that the ſerious peruſal of the premi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes (intended only for their information, reformation, not perdition) may at laſt induce them for ever hereafter to ſtop both their ears againſt the enchanting ſongs of all <hi>Romiſh Syrens,</hi> and open both their ears and hearts cordially to embrace this ſacred counſell of God himſelf, they have ſo long obſtinately trampled under feet, Prov. 24.21, 22. <hi>My Son fear thou the Lord and the King, and meddle not with Changers, or thoſe who are given to change, for their cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity ſhall ſodenly ariſe</hi> (as we have ſeen by many late expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riments, in the very making, acting of all our late publick changes) <hi>and who knoweth the ruine of them both?</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
